# Kseniia ILCHENKO

#### **Contacts**

#### Address:

78510 France (IDF)

#### Phone:

+ 33 (6) 659 521 63

#### Email:

kseniia.ilchenko@gmail.com

#### LinkedIn:

https://www.linkedin.com/in/kse niia-ilchenko-9125941a/

### Upwork:

http://www.upwork.com/o/profiles/users/\_~01179f5a56d9c2ae82

## Languages

English Ukrainian

French Russian

### Soft Skills

- Decision making
- Critical thinking

Multi-

- Problem solving
- taskingAdaptability

# EmpathyHard Skills

- Blockchain
- Python (Pandas, Scikitlearn, Skipy, Streamlit, etc)
- BI: Sisense, Clicdata,
  PowerBI, Klipfolio, Google
  Data Studio
- SAS (Certified), Stata
- MS Office, Libre Office, WSP, VBA, PowerQuery
- SQL
- Team management
- Product development

#### Summary

Certified product owner (PSPO I). Strong background in economic modelling, ML and AI techniques for data analysis and forecasting. Experienced in project management for data and blockchain solutions, data management automation, automated dashboard creation, and financial modelling. Passionate about education and scientific research.

### **Experience**

Consultant - from 09/2021 Globex Innovations, UK

Lead Data Analytics Teacher - from 10/2021 Ironhack, France

Business Analyst/Head of Product Analytics – from 01/2021 IntellectEU, Belgium

- Project and product management for blockchain solutions
- Products launch for SWIFT-related products
- Cross-border payment forecasts (clusterization, time series)
- Wealth management models (knowledge graphs)
- Data analysis and evaluation of information
- Collaborate with developers and subject matter experts to establish the technical vision and analyze tradeoffs between usability and performance needs

Lecturer - from 09/2021 ESSCA, France

• Development of the syllabus and teaching the Business Analytics course

Full-Stack Data Scientist via Upwork.com – 10/2015 to 12/2020

CongentBI, UK (remote) Chief Data Scientist

- Organization of the full data life cycle, data consolidation and KPIs analysis
- · Clustering and segmentation
- Development of educational dashboards on Sisense and Clicdata
- Project management and team management, Product Owner, cooperation with the marketing team

#### AutoPilot Reviews, LLC, USA (remote) Data Analyst

- Benchmark reports, traffic analysis and financial dashboarding
- · Segmentation of clients, churn forecast

### Applied Science Nutrition, Canada (remote) Data Analyst

- Automatization of financial reporting
- Data consolidation, analysis of traffic

#### Data Scientist - 06/2020 to 12/2020 BPCE, Paris

- AML/FT analysis
- Development of the approach for minimizing the number of treated alerts.
- Fraud detection, imbalanced data, supervised and unsupervised learning, results visualization

# Head of Laboratory – 01/2015 to 10/2016 World Data Center for Geoinformatics and Sustainable Development (WDS-ICSU), Kyiv

- Data collection, processing, models creation and validation
- Descriptive and prescriptive analysis
- Grant programs and start-up competitions, international relations
- Project management
- Development of educational programs

Investment raising for the project "Foresight of economy of Ukraine" (\$2mln), grant support from Science and Technology Center of Ukraine (\$100K). Development of the master program in data science with major in decision support.

# Senior Lecturer - 09/2015 to 07/2016 Institute for Applied System Analysis, Kyiv

- Teaching and scientific research
- Supervision of master thesis

#### Lecturer - 09/2015 to 08/2016 Taras Shevchenko National University of Kyiv, Kyiv

- Teaching and scientific research
- Responsible for the preparation and governmental licencing the program for PhD studies at major "Computer Science and Information Technology"
- Deputy Head of Scientific Council of the faculty
- Head of association of young scientists of the faculty

# Assistant Professor - 09/2010-08/2015 National Technical University of Ukraine «Kyiv Polytechnic Institute», Kyiv

- Teaching and scientific research
- Supervising bachelor/master theses

The bachelor thesis entitled "Modeling of Sustainable Development for Municipalities Using the Complex Indicators' structure" won Ethics and Operational Research Award 2015 at EURO 2015, Glasgow, UK.

# Research Associate - 02/2014-12/2014 Laboratory for Computer Modeling and Intelligent Data Analysis at World Data Center for Geoinformatics and Sustainable Development, Kyiv

• data analysis, modeling of complex systems in terms of sustainable development, analysis of global threats

# **Education**

M2: Economic engineering and data analysis – 2019-2020

**University Cergy-Pontoise**, France

Fellowship: Nonproliferation and Terrorism Studies – 2014

Center for Nonproliferation Studies of Middlebury University, USA

PhD: Economics (Math methods, models and IT in economics) - 2010-2014

National Technical University "Kyiv Polytechnic Institute", Ukraine

MA: Intellectual property - 2012-2013

National University "Odesa Academy of Law", Ukraine

MSc: Economic cybernetics – 2008-2010

National Technical University "Kyiv Polytechnic Institute", Ukraine

BSc: Economic cybernetics – 2004-2008

National Technical University "Kyiv Polytechnic Institute", Ukraine

# **Certifications and courses**

- Professional Scrum Product Owner (PSPO I)
- SAS Certified Specialist: Base Programming using 9.4
- TOEIC 975/990
- CODATA-RDA school of scientific research
- Introduction to data science, business analysis and artificial intelligence
- Introduction to GIS for SDI
- Grid computing and metacomputing technology research

# **Pro bono activities**

• member of the stream «Initiatives for OR Education» organizing committee of EURO Conference in Operation Research

## **Selected Publications**

JM Garcia-López, *K Ilchenko*, O Nazarenko. Optimization Lab Sessions: Major Features and Applications of IBM CPLEX. Optimization and Decision Support Systems for Supply Chain, 2017

*K. Ilchenko*, A. Lisogor. Sustainable Development Modeling For Municipalities. Theoretical and Empirical Researches in Urban Management (TERUM)", 2016. http://um.ase.ro/no111/5.pdf

*K. Ilchenko* et. al. Ukraine's economy Foresight for mid-term (2015-2020) and long-term (2020-2030 years) time horizons / The Head of the research Prof. M. Zgurovsky / International Council for Science (ICSU); National Technical University of Ukraine "Kyiv Polytechnic Institute"; Institute for Applied Systems Analysis of MES and NAS of Ukraine; World Data Center for Geoinformatics and Sustainable Development, 2015 <a href="http://wdc.org.ua/sites/default/files/WDC-IASA-FORSIGHT-UA.pdf">http://wdc.org.ua/sites/default/files/WDC-IASA-FORSIGHT-UA.pdf</a>

*K. Ilchenko*. The Nonproliferation Index as a Quantitative Assessment of the Balance between State's Interests and International Peacekeeping. Materials of OR for Developing Countries Workshop, 2015.

*K. Ilchenko*, I. Pyshnograiev. A Composite Indicator of K-society Measurement. Materials of the 11th International Conference on ICT in Education, Research and Industrial Applications: Integration, Harmonization and Knowledge Transfer, 2015.

*K. Ilchenko*. Modeling the Strategy of Loan and Deposit activities of Commercial Banks. Business Inform, 2014.

*K. Ilchenko*. The proliferation threat as a part of sustainable development index. Proceedings of 27 International Operation Research Conference EURO 2015, 2015.